My name is Ryan Lobo,
إسمى ريان لوبو،
and I've been involved in the documentary
وقد كنت مشاركاً فى
filmmaking business all over the world for the last 10 years.
صناعة الأفلام التوثيقية حول العالم خلال ال 10 سنوات الماضية.
During the process of making these films
خلال عملية إنتاج هذه الأفلام
I found myself taking photographs,
وجدت نفسى أقوم بالتقاط صور،
often much to the annoyance of the video cameramen.
غالباً بسبب الإنزعاج من مصورى الفيديو
I found this photography of mine almost compulsive.
وجدت أن هذا التصوير الذى أقوم بة مُلْزِم
And at the end of a shoot, I would sometimes feel that
وفى نهاية التصوير ، أحس فى بعض الأحيان بأن
I had photographs that told a better story
بأن لدى صور فوتوغرافية تحكى قصة أفضل
than a sometimes-sensational documentary.
فى بعض الأحيان من الأفلام الوثائقية المثيرة
I felt, when I had my photographs,
شعرت، عندما كان لدى هذة الصور،
that I was holding on to something true,
بأن لدى شئ حقيقى ،
regardless of agendas or politics.
بغض النظر عن الأجندات أو السياسة.
In 2007, I traveled to three war zones.
سافرت فى عام 2007 إلى 3 مناطق حرب.
I traveled to Iraq, Afghanistan and Liberia.
سافرت إلى العراق ، أفغانستان و ليبريا.
And over there I experienced
وواجهت هنالك
other people's suffering, up close and personal,
معاناة الأخرين عن قرب،
immersed myself in some rather intense and emotional stories,
غمست نفسى فى قصص عاطفية و مكثفة،
and at times I experienced great fear for my own life.
وفى بعض الأحيان شعرت بخوف شديد على حياتى.
As always, I would return to Bangalore,
كما هو الحال دائماً ، فاننى سوف أعود إلى بانغالور،
and often to animated discussions at friend's homes,
وغالباً تكون هنالك مناقشات حيوية فى منزل أحد الأصدقاء،
where we would discuss various issues
حيث نتناقش فى مختلف القضايا
while they complained bitterly about the new pub timings,
في حين يشتكوا بمرارة من توقيت الحانة جديدة ،
where a drink often cost more than what they'd paid
حيث يكلف الشراب أكثر مما يدفعوا
their 14-year-old maid.
الى خادمتهم ذات الـ14 عاماً.
I would feel very isolated during these discussions.
أشعر بأننى معزول جداً خلال هذة المناقشات.
But at the same time, I questioned myself
ولكن فى نفس الوقت ، سألت نفسى
and my own integrity and purpose in storytelling.
ونزاهتى وغرضي الخاص من قص الحكايات.
And I decided that I had compromised,
وقد قررت أننى قد حصلت على التسوية،
just like my friends in those discussions,
تماماً مثل أصدقائى فى تلك المناقشات،
where we told stories
حيث روينا قصصً
in contexts we made excuses for,
فى سياق قمنا بصنع الأعذار فية،
rather than taking responsibility for.
بدلاً عن تحمل المسؤلية.
I won't go into details about what led to a decision I made,
لن أخوض فى تفاصيل ماقادنى إلى قرار إتخذته،
but let's just say it involved alcohol, cigarettes,
ولكن دعنا نقول فقط أنه ينطوي على الكحول والسجائر ،
other substances and a woman.
وأشياء أخرى و إمرأة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I basically decided that it was I,
قررت أننى أنا فى الأساس،
not the camera or the network,
وليس الكاميرا أو الشبكة،
or anything that lay outside myself,
أو أى شئ أخر حولى،
that was the only instrument in storytelling
الوسيلة الوحيدة فى روى القصص
truly worth tuning.
تستحق التوليف.
In my life, when I tried to achieve things
عندما كنت أحاول أن أحقق أشياء فى حياتى
like success or recognition, they eluded me.
مثل النجاح أو الشهرة، كانت تستعصى على.
Paradoxically, when I let go of these objectives,
ومن المفارقات ، عندما تركت هذة الأشياء،
and worked from a place of compassion and purpose,
وعملت من مكان للشفقة،
looking for excellence, rather than the results of it,
بحثاً عن التميز ، وليس على نتائجة ،
everything arrived on its own, including fulfillment.
كل شئ أتى من تلقاء نفسة ، متضمناً الرضاء.
Photography transcended culture, including my own.
التصوير الفوتغرافى تجاوز الثقافة، بما فيها تقافتى.
And it is, for me, a language which expressed the intangible,
وهو، بالنسبة إلى، عبارة عن لغة تعبر عن الأشياء الغامضة،
and gives voice to people and stories without.
ويعطى للناس حكايات بلا صوت.
I invite you into three recent stories of mine,
إنى أدعيكم إلى ثلاثة قصص حديثة،
which are about this way of looking, if you will,
التى هى حول هذة الطريقة فى النظر، اذا الصح التعبير،
which I believe exemplify the tenets
التى اعتقد إنها تجسد مبادئ
of what I like to call compassion in storytelling.
ما أود تسميتة الرحمة فى القص.
In 2007 I went to Liberia,
فى عام 2007 ذهبت الى ليبريا،
where a group of my friends and I
حيث قمت مع مجموعة من أصدقائى
did an independent, self-funded film, still in progress,
بعمل فلم مستقل ، ممول ذاتياً ، و مايزال العمل جارياً،
on a very legendary and brutal war-lord
حول وحشية أسطورة لورد حرب
named General Butt Naked.
يدعى الجنرال بات نايكد (المؤخرة العارية).
His real name is Joshua, and he's pictured here in a cell
إسمة الحقيقى جوشوا، وهو فى هذة الصورة فى زنزانة
where he once used to torture and murder people,
حيث كان يستخدمها فى تعذيب و قتل الناس،
including children.
بمن فيهم الأطفال.
Joshua claims to have personally killed
جوشوا يدعي أنه شخصياً قتل
more than 10,000 people during Liberia's civil war.
مايزيد عن 10 اَلاف شخص خلال الحرب الأهلية فى ليبريا
He got his name from fighting stark naked.
حصل على إسمه من القتال عارياً.
And he is probably the most prolific mass murderer
وانه ربما كان من أغزر السفاحين
alive on Earth today.
على قيد الحياة على الأرض اليوم.
This woman witnessed the General murdering her brother.
شاهدت هذة المرأة الجنرال يقتل شقيقها.
Joshua commanded his child-soldiers to commit unspeakable crimes,
أمر جوشوا جنودة الأطفال بارتكاب جرائم يعجز عنها الوصف،
and enforced his command with great brutality.
وفرض قيادتة بوحشية شديدة.
Today many of these children are addicted to drugs like heroin,
العديد من هؤلاء الأطفال اليوم من المدمنين على المخدرات مثل الهيروين ،
and they are destitute, like these young men in the image.
ويعانوا من الفقر المدقع ، مثل هؤلاء الشباب فى هذة الصورة.
How do you live with yourself
كيف يمكن أن تعيش مع نفسك
if you know you've committed horrific crimes?
إذا كنت تعرف أنك إرتكبت هذة الجرائم المروعة ؟
Today the General is a baptized Christian evangelist.
عُمد الجنرال اليوم كمبشر مسيحى.
And he's on a mission.
وهو فى مهمة.
We accompanied Joshua, as he walked the Earth,
صاحبنا جوشوا ، وهو يسير على الأرض،
visiting villages where he had once killed and raped.
يزور القرى حيث قتل و إغتصب من قبل.
He seeked forgiveness,
يبحث عن الغفران،
and he claims to endeavor to improve
ويدعي أنه يسعى إلى تحسين
the lives of his child-soldiers.
حياة جنودة الأطفال.
During this expedition I expected him
خلال هذة الرحلة كنت أتوقع
to be killed outright, and us as well.
أن يقُتل الجنرال على الفور، و نحن معة.
But what I saw opened my eyes
ولكن ما رأيتة فتح أعينى
to an idea of forgiveness
على فكرة التسامح
which I never thought possible.
التى لم أتوقع أبداً أن تكون ممكنة.
In the midst of incredible poverty and loss,
فى خضم الفقر و خسارة لا توصف،
people who had nothing absolved a man
الناس الذين لم يكن لديهم شيئاً غفروا لرجل
who had taken everything from them.
أخذ كل شئ منهم.
He begs for forgiveness,
توسل للمغفرة ،
and receives it from the same woman
وحصل عليها من نفس المرأة
whose brother he murdered.
التى قام بقتل شقيقها.
Senegalese, the young man seated on the wheelchair here,
سنغالس، هذا الشاب الذى يجلس على الكرسى المتحرك هنا،
was once a child soldier, under the General's command,
كان طفل مقاتل من قبل، تحت قيادة الجنرال،
until he disobeyed orders,
حتى عصى الأوامر،
and the General shot off both his legs.
فقام الجنرال باطلاق النار على ساقية.
He forgives the General in this image.
غفر للجنرال فى هذا الصورة.
He risked his life as he walked up to people
خاطر الجنرال بحياتة حين ذهب الى أناس
whose families he'd murdered.
قام بقتل عائلاتهم من قبل.
In this photograph a hostile crowd in a slum surrounds him.
في هذه الصورة حشد معاد في الأحياء الفقيرة المحيطة به.
And Joshua remains silent
وجوشوا يظل صامتاً
as they vented their rage against him.
حين صبوا غضبهم ضدة.
This image, to me, is almost like from a Shakespearean play,
هذه الصورة ، بالنسبة لي ، تقريبا مثل مسرحية من شكسبير،
with a man, surrounded by various influences,
مع رجل ، تحيط بة مختلف التأثيرات،
desperate to hold on to something true within himself,
يائساُ للتمسك بشئ حقيقى فى داخل نفسة،
in a context of great suffering that he has created himself.
فى سياق معاناة كبيرة صنعها بنفسة.
I was intensely moved during all this.
لقد تحركت بشكل مكثف خلال كل هذا.
But the question is,
ولكن السؤال هو،
does forgiveness and redemption replace justice?
هل يحل الغفران والخلاص محل العدالة؟
Joshua, in his own words, says that he does not mind
جوشوا، فى كلماتة، يقول أنة لا يمانع
standing trial for his crimes,
أن يخضع للمحاكمة على جرائمة،
and speaks about them from soapboxes across Monrovia,
و يتحدث عنهم من منصات صغيرة في جميع أنحاء مونروفيا ،
to an audience that often includes his victims.
لجمهور غالبا يتضمن ضحاياة.
A very unlikely spokesperson for the idea of
شخص مستبعد للتحدث عن فكرة
separation of church and state.
الفصل بين الكنيسة والدولة.
The second story I'm going to tell you about
القصة الثانية التى سوف أخبركم بها
is about a group of very special fighting women
عن مجموعة مميزة من النساء المقاتلات
with rather unique peace-keeping skills.
بمهارات فريدة لحفظ السلام.
Liberia has been devastated by one of Africa's
تعرضت ليبريا للدمار من واحدة
bloodiest civil wars,
من أعنف الحروب الأهلية فى أفريقيا،
which has left more than 200,000 people dead,
التى أودت بحياة أكثر من 200 ألف شخص،
thousands of women scarred by rape and crime
الاَلاف من النساء تضضرن من جراء اللإغتصاب و الجرائم
on a spectacular scale.
على نطاق مذهل.
Liberia is now home
ليبريا الأن منزل
to an all-woman United Nations contingent
الأمم المتحدة لوحدات
of Indian peacekeepers.
حفظ السلام للنساء فى الهند
These women, many from small towns in India,
العديد من هؤلاء النساء، من مدن صغيرة فى الهند،
help keep the peace, far away from home and family.
يساعدن فى حفظ السلام، بعيداً عن منازلهم وأسرهم.
They use negotiation and tolerance
يستخدمن التفاوض و التسامح
more often than an armed response.
فى كثير من الأحيان من رد الفعل المسلح.
The commander told me that a woman could gauge
قال لى القائد أن المرأة يمكنها قياس
a potentially violent situation
حالة العنف المحتمل
much better than men.
أفضل بكثير من الرجال.
And that they were definitely capable of diffusing it non-aggressively.
وإنهم بالتأكيد أكثر قدرة على نزع فتيل العنف بطريقة غير عدوانية.
This man was very drunk,
هذا الرجل كان مخمور بشدة،
and he was very interested in my camera,
وكان مهتم جداً بالكاميرا،
until he noticed the women, who handled him
حتى لاحظ النساء، واللواتى تعاملن معة
with smiles, and AK-47s at the ready, of course.
بابتسامة، وكلاشنكوف على أهبة الاستعداد، بطبيعة الحال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This contingent seems to be quite lucky,
هذة الوحدات تبدو محظوظة جداً،
and it has not sustained any casualties,
ولم تتكبد أى خسائر بشرية،
even though dozens of peacekeepers have been killed in Liberia.
على الرغم من العشرات من قوات حفظ السلام قتلوا فى ليبريا.
And yes, all of those people killed were male.
ونعم، كل هؤلاء الذين قتلوا كانو رجال.
Many of the women are married with children,
العديد من النساء متزوجات و لديهن أطفال،
and they say the hardest part of their deployment
ويقولن أن الجزء الأصعب فى عملهم
was being kept away from their children.
هو أنهن بعيدات عن أطفالهن.
I accompanied these women on their patrols,
لقد صحابت هؤلاء النساء فى دورياتهن،
and watched as they walked past men,
شاهدت أثناء سيرهن بين رجال،
many who passed very lewd comments incessantly.
العديد منهم من علق تعليقات بذيئة بلا إنقطاع.
And when I asked one of the women about the shock and awe response,
وعندما سألت أحد النساء إذاء الرد بذهول أو الصدمة،
she said, "Don't worry, same thing back home.
قالت لى،"لا تقلق، نفس الشئ يحدث هنالك فى الوطن.
We know how to deal with these fellows,"
ونحن نعرف كيف نتعامل مع هؤلاء الأشخاص،"
and ignored them.
وتجاهلتهم.
In a country ravaged by violence against women,
فى بلد يمزقة العنف تجاة المرأة،
Indian peacekeepers have inspired many local women
قوات حفظ السلام الهندية ألهمت العديد من النساء المحليات
to join the police force.
للإنضمام الى قوات الشرطة.
Sometimes, when the war is over and all the film crews have left,
أحيانا ، عندما إنتهت الحرب ، و غادرجميع طاقم الفيلم،
the most inspiring stories are the ones
أكثر القصص إلهاماً
that float just beneath the radar.
هى التى مرت من تحت الرادار.
I came back to India and nobody was interested in buying the story.
رجعت الى الهند ولم يكن أحد مهتماً بشراء القصة.
And one editor told me that she wasn't interested
قالت لى أحدى المحررات أنها ليست مهتمة
in doing what she called "manual labor stories."
في القيام بما وصفته ب "قصص العمل اليدوي".
In 2007 and 2009 I did stories on the Delhi Fire Service, the DFS,
فى عام 2007 و عام 2009 عملت قصص حول إدارة إطفاء الحرائق بدلهى،
which, during the summer, is probably the world's most active fire department.
والتى، خلال فصل الصيف، ربما تكون اكثر الإدارات فى العالم أنشغالاً.
They answer more than 5,000 calls in just two months.
فهم يجيبوا على أكثر من 5 الاَف مكالمة خلال شهرين فقط.
And all this against incredible logistical odds,
وكل هذا ضد إحتمالات لوجستية لاتصدق،
like heat and traffic jams.
مثل الحرارة و إختناقات المرور.
Something amazing happened during this shoot.
شئ مدهش حدث خلال هذا التصوير.
Due to a traffic jam, we were late in getting to a slum,
نظراً لإزدحام المرور، كنا قد تأخرنا فى الوصول إلى أحد الأحياء الفقيرة،
a large slum, which had caught fire.
أحد الأحياء الفقيرة الكبيرة ، التي كانت قد اشتعلت فيها النيران.
As we neared, angry crowds attacked our trucks
عند إقترابنا ، هاجمت جموع غاضبة شاحناتنا
and stoned them, by hundreds of people all over the place.
والقى عليهم الحجارة ، من قبل مئات من الأشخاص من كل المكان.
These men were terrified,
هؤلاء الرجال كانوا في حالة ذعر ،
as the mob attacked our vehicle.
عندما هاجمت العصابات شاحناتنا.
But nonetheless, despite the hostility,
ولكنهم مع ذلك ، على الرغم من العداء ،
firefighters left the vehicle and successfully fought the fire.
ترك رجال الإطفاء السيارة، ونجحوا فى التصدى للنيران.
Running the gauntlet through hostile crowds,
أداروا العملية من خلال الحشود العدائية،
and some wearing motorbike helmets to prevent injury.
وبعضهم يرتدي خوذة دراجة نارية لمنع الإصابة.
Some of the local people forcibly took away the hoses
بعض السكان المحلين أخذوا خراطيم المياة عنوة
from the firemen to put out the fire in their homes.
من من رجال الاطفاء لإخماد الحريق في منازلهم.
Now, hundreds of homes were destroyed.
المئات من المنازل قد دمرت.
But the question that lingered in my mind was,
ولكن السؤال الذى دار فى ذهنى كان ،
what causes people to destroy fire trucks
ما الذى دفع بالناس لتدمير سيارات الإطفاء
headed to their own homes?
المتجهة الى منازلهم؟
Where does such rage come from?
مين أين أتى كل هذا الغضب؟
And how are we responsible for this?
وكيف كنا المسؤلين عن ذلك ؟
45 percent of the 14 million people
45 بالمئة من ال 14 مليون شخص
who live in Delhi live in unauthorized slums,
الذين يعيشون فى دلهى يعيشوا فى أحياء فقيرة غير مصرح بها،
which are chronically overcrowded.
والتى مكتظة بشكل كبير.
They lack even the most basic amenities.
حتى أنهم يفتقرون إلى أبسط وسائل الراحة.
And this is something that is common to all our big cities.
وهذا أمر شائع في جميع مدننا الكبرى.
Back to the DFS. A huge chemical depot caught fire,
نعود إلى إدارة إطفاء الحرائق، إشتعلت النيران فى مستودع كيميائى ضخم،
thousands of drums filled with petrochemicals
الآلاف من البراميل مملوءة بالبتروكيماويات
were blazing away and exploding all around us.
وقد اشتعلت فيها النيران وكانت تنفجر في كل مكان حولنا.
The heat was so intense, that hoses were used
كانت الحرارة شديدة، لدرجة أن خراطيم المياة كانت تستخدم
to cool down firefighters
لتبريد رجال الإطفاء
fighting extremely close to the fire, and with no protective clothing.
الذين كانوا يحاربون النيران عن قرب، و دون إردتداء ملابس واقية.
In India we often love to complain about our government bodies.
إننا كثيرا ما نحب أن نتذمر من الهيئات الحكومية فى الهند.
But over here, the heads of the DFS,
ولكن هنا، رؤساء إدارة إطفاء الحرائق،
Mr. R.C. Sharman, Mr. A.K. Sharman,
الأستاذ اَر. سى. شيرمان ، والأستاذ اَة. كَه. شيرمان،
led the firefight with their men.
قادوا عملية الإطفاء مع رجالهم.
Something wonderful in a country where
شيء رائع في بلد حيث
manual labor is often looked down upon.
العمل اليدوى غالباً مايُنظرإلية بازدراء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Over the years, my faith in the power of storytelling has been tested.
على مر السنين ، وإيماني في قوة القص قد اخُتبر.
And I've had very serious doubt about its efficacy,
وقد ساورنى شك خطير حول فاعليتة،
and my own faith in humanity.
وإيماني الخاص في الانسانية.
However, a film we shot still airs on the National Geographic channel.
ومع ذلك ، فإن الفيلم الذى قمنا بتصويرة لا يزال يبث على قناة ناشيونال جيوغرافيك.
And when it airs I get calls from all the guys I was with
وعندما تم بثة تلقيت مكالمات من جميع الرجال الذين كنت معهم
and they tell me that they receive hundreds of calls congratulating them.
جميعهم يقولون لي أنهم تلقوا مئات من المكالمات تهنئتهم.
Some of the firemen told me that they were also inspired
بعض من رجال الاطفاء قالو لي أنهم كانوا أيضا اُلهموا
to do better because they were so pleased
لبذل المزيد من الجهد لأنهم كانو مسرورين جداً
to get thank-yous rather than brick bats.
بالحصول على الشكر بدلا عن الطوب و العصى.
It seems that this story helped change perceptions about the DFS,
يبدو أن هذه القصة قد ساعدت في تغيير التصورات عن إدارة إطفاء الحرائق ،
at least in the minds of an audience in part on televisions,
على الأقل في أذهان جمهور جزء منه على التلفزيون ،
read magazines and whose huts aren't on fire.
قراءة المجلات والذين أكواخهم ليست مشتعلة فيها النيران.
Sometimes, focusing on what's heroic, beautiful and dignified,
في بعض الأحيان ، التركيز على ما هو بطولي ، جميل ومشرف ،
regardless of the context,
بغض النظر عن السياق،
can help magnify these intangibles three ways,
يمكن أن يساعد على تضخيم هذة الممتلكات بثلاثة طرق،
in the protagonist of the story, in the audience,
في بطل القصة ، في الحضور ،
and also in the storyteller.
وأيضاً فى راوى القصة.
And that's the power of storytelling.
وتلك هى قوة القص.
Focus on what's dignified, courageous and beautiful,
التركيز على ما هو كرامة وشجاعة ومشرف ،
and it grows. Thank you.
وسوف تنموا وتكبر، شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)